<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The remonstrance made by the Queene-mother of France, to the King her sonne, for remedy of such disorders and abuses as she pretendeth to be in the present gouernement and managing of the affaires of state, in the realme of France Particularly manifesting the authors thereof, with their supposed, ambitious practises and dangerous designes, threatning desolation and ruine vnto that kingdome. Faithfully translated out of French.</title>
            <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847635</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07150)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 996:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The remonstrance made by the Queene-mother of France, to the King her sonne, for remedy of such disorders and abuses as she pretendeth to be in the present gouernement and managing of the affaires of state, in the realme of France Particularly manifesting the authors thereof, with their supposed, ambitious practises and dangerous designes, threatning desolation and ruine vnto that kingdome. Faithfully translated out of French.</title>
                  <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathanaell Newbery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Star vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  1610-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12685:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12685:1"/>
            <p>THE REMONSTRANCE made by the <hi>Queene-mother</hi> of
<hi>France,</hi> to the KING her Sonne, for remedy of ſuch diſorders and abuſes as She pretendeth to be in the preſent Gouernement and managing of affaires of State, in the Realme of FRANCE. Particularly manifeſting the Authors thereof, with their ſuppoſed, ambitious practiſes and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Deſignes, threatning Deſolation and Ruine vnto that KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Imprinted by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanaell Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Star vnder S.
<hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12685:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12685:2"/>
            <head>An Aduertiſement to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader:</hi> This <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> is not preſented to thy view, to the end to gaine credit to the pretended reaſons thereof, but that thou mighteſt ſee vnder what colours and diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they reuolt, to hide their owne ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deſignements, whoſe end is onely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garboyle the <hi>State,</hi> and whoſe counſailes haue alwaies beene vnder pretext of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good to obtrude their priuate diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, by caſting thoſe aſperſions on the <hi>State,</hi> and the publique Miniſters thereof, with<pb facs="tcp:12685:3"/>which themſelues haue beene chiefly tainted I had thought to haue ioyned the anſwere to theſe reaſons, which I ſhortly expect: But becauſe I gueſſe that to euery indifferent mans vnderſtanding, they may anſwere themſelues by their owne inſufficiency and nullity, I haue aduentured to proceede to publication, before the other party hath put in their anſwere.</p>
            <trailer>Vale &amp; fruere.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12685:3"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT of the Reaſons and Complaynts made by the
<hi>Queene-Mother</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to the KING her Sonne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Queene-mother</hi> is much grieued, and complaineth, that ſhee being borne a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of one of the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious houſes in <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; hauing had the honor to be the wife of one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Kings that euer raigned in <hi>France,</hi> and mother to the King at this preſent raigning; that after ſhee hath with many perills, dangers &amp; cares, during the minority of the King her Sonne, preſerued and gouerned the Realme: In recompence of her ſo great paines, and mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection, ſhee hath bin ſhamefully driuen from the Court, and from the preſence and company of the King her Sonne, and the reſt of her children, and reſtrained as a priſoner in <hi>Blois,</hi> with all ſorts of indignities, without any reſpect of her birth, or of<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12685:4"/>ſo many great Princes, to whom ſhe hath the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be allyed; and againſt the honour due to the memorie of the late King her husband, and of the King her ſonne: and that wholy by the aduiſe and counſells of <hi>Luynes</hi> his brethren, &amp; adherents, thereby the more eaſily, during the minority of the King, to vſurpe the authoritie Royall, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the
<hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Queene</hi> likewiſe complaineth, that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aforeſaid, abuſing the youth and fauour of the King, haue in ſuch manner continued and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in their miſchieuous diſſeigns, that not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the moſt barbarous crueltie that may or can be vſed againſt the moſt vnworthy and abiect perſon in the world, they haue cauſed her beſt and moſt faithfull houſhold-Seruants to be ſeparated from her, and diuers others for her ſake to be committed to Priſon, without reaſon or iuſtice; contrarie to the ordinary proceedings of the Realme.</p>
            <p>Prohibiting all perſons of what eſtate ſoeuer to viſite, and frequent or repaire vnto her, as if She had beene guilty of high-treaſon, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement not to goe or walke aboue a Myle out of the Towne of
<hi>Blois.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And appointed <hi>Monſieur de Roiſſy</hi> to watch and haue regard to her actions; ſuborned her Seruants to betray her, ſending a number of meſſengers one after the other within the ſpace of two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty weekes, with a thouſand falſe promiſes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12685:4"/>her acceſſe againe vnto his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> the rather to mocke her, and to increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her afflictions.</p>
            <p>Marrying her Daughter to a ſtrange Prince, without her knowledge or preſence, that her diſgrace might be the manifeſter to all Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome, and to all the Realme of <hi>France.</hi> And for the full accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of all their wickedneſſe and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, cauſed the King to reſolue vpon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of the reſt of her dayes in the Caſtle of <hi>Amboiſe,</hi> or ſome other place, in their cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            <p>Whereof hauing faithfull intelligence, by one of thoſe whom they confidently truſt in their moſt ſecret affaires, ſhee was conſtrayned by night to make her eſcape, and to retire to the Duke <hi>D'Eſpernon,</hi> to make her retrait ſure in the Towne of <hi>Angouleſme:</hi> That being there in ſafety out of her enemies hands, ſhee might with more libertie let his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> vnderſtand the cruell and inhumane dealings which ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the perſons aboue-named, and to giue him aduiſe of the diſorders which ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cauſe and procure within the Realme; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the remedies fit and conuenient to ſtay them.</p>
            <p>And to beginne with their bad behauiours. It is to be conſidered what ſiniſter and artefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubtilties they vſed, to conſtraine the Court<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12685:5"/>of <hi>Parliament</hi> to giue ſentence againſt the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall <hi>D'Ancre,</hi> by falſe accuſations, to make a pray of him; whereof perceiuing themſelues to be aſſured, to get more abſolute commaund, counſelled the King to keepe the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> priſoner, with the Princeſſe his wife, by whoſe meanes and her captiuitie together, ſhee hath loſt three children, for whoſe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Queene-mother</hi> truly confeſſeth, and proteſteth before God, that ſhe neuer was more grieued then that by euill counſell, and falſe intelligence, ſhee had beene induced thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, hauing ſince knowne the truth of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, whereof ſhe will aſſure the King, and moſt humbly beſeech him, to ſet him at libertie, both for the good of this Realme, and of the ſaid Prince.</p>
            <p>The perfidious treaſons, practiſes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments of Innocent perſons, is alſo to be noted, wherewith they ſerued their turnes; to get the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> into the cuſtody of
<hi>Monſieur de Vitry,</hi> &amp; <hi>Monſieur de Peiſan</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law, thereby to haue him in their hands. And what boldneſſe is in them, to make &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a new regiment, to keepe him more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, and to haue the force and power of armes in their hands? whereunto muſt be added, the preſumption and boldneſſe by them vſed, to induce the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> to ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity (that to deliuer the ſaid Prince her<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12685:5"/>brother) ſhe ſhould marry
<hi>Cadenet,</hi> to the end, that by the meanes of ſo ſtrict a fauour and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, they might vnder the protection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (to the great preiudice of the King) preſerue their power and authoritie?</p>
            <p>And further to make their pernicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes manifeſt and euident, euery man ſeeth, how they haue put from attending on the Kings perſon, Monſieur <hi>de Breues,</hi> a man cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and appoynted by the late King, for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and one that worthily diſcharged his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in that reſpect, to put him into the hands of one of their confident friends, whereof they were formerly glad, and thought themſelues happy to be domeſticall ſeruants. The Earle of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> for his part, hath not beene exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from being obſerued, and they haue not fayled to haue regard to his gouernement, by perſons that prie into his actions.</p>
            <p>Touching the Princes, Dukes, Peeres, and Officers of the Crowne, and other Lords of this Realme, they haue beene wholly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the intelligence and gouernement of the affayres of eſtate, to giue the entire ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof to <hi>Modene, Du Hagent,</hi> Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>D'Othano,</hi> and <hi>Marſillai,</hi> perſons altogether vnworthy and incapable of their charges.</p>
            <p>The entertainement they haue giuen to the Duke
<hi>D'Eſpernon,</hi> after his long and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice done to this Crowne, ſufficiently<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12685:6"/>witneſſe, their inſolence, hauing proceeded ſo farre, as to make him the Kings priſoner, and after, cauſed him to be ſent to <hi>Metz,</hi> vnder pretence of imaginarie affaires of
<hi>Bohemia;</hi> to procure ſome credite to be giuen to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and to execute the functions of his charge of Colonell of the Infanterie: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto muſt be added the perſecutions, which for his ſake haue beene layde vpon Marſhall <hi>de Roquelance,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Tilladet,</hi> and <hi>la Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſſelles du Tillet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the Marſhall <hi>de Bouillon,</hi> the great contempt that hath beene made of his qualitie and power, vſing him with all ſorts of indifferencie, ſufficiently ſheweth how they would cauſe the King to looſe the affection of the greateſt perſonages of the Realme, and thoſe that are able to ſerue him worthily.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Montmorencie,</hi> hath alſo expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimented and well tryed their impudencie, by the effectes which they haue giuen to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame the Conſtable, his Mother in lawe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken her from the perſon of the Queene, to place Madame <hi>Luyne,</hi> and their Siſter, in her ſtead, to the end, that no body may haue acceſſe to their Maieſties, but by their means. The ſayd Duke <hi>de Montmorencie,</hi> in that which concerneth his charge and gouernement, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued all ſorts of diſcontentments, by the bad offices which they haue done him<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12685:6"/>about the King.</p>
            <p>It is well knowne, what great perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they haue vſed towardes Monſieur <hi>le Grand,</hi> for the affaires of the Duke d'<hi>Eſpernon,</hi> and of Monſieur <hi>de Vitry:</hi> And how that in the great ſickeneſſe which hee had in <hi>Paris</hi> the laſt yeare, thinking he would haue dyed, they had obtained the reuerſion of his Offices, by that meanes fruſtrating the merits and deſerts of the ſeruice of the Baron <hi>de Termes</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Of all the Offices that haue beene voyde ſince the time of their fauour with the King, from the greateſt to the leaſt, none haue eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, which they haue not retayned for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to be eyther ſould or giuen to thoſe that are of their fraternitie; and euery day doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but gape for the death of thoſe that haue good and great Offices, to make their profite of them, to the ruine and dammage of ſuch as for their vertues and ſeruices, are iuſtly to be rewarded and recompenced.</p>
            <p>Touching the Kings treaſure, they haue and boldely doe diſpoſe thereof at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, without any contradiction, and haue drawne it ſo drie, that the King and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, are thereby greatly indamaged.</p>
            <p>Touching the forme and dignitie royall, to order all things, and to appoynt and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine all affayres, and times of audience, they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12685:7"/>onely doe it, playing the Kings; propoſing, and reſoluing vpon the great affaires of this Realme, without calling any other thereunto, but thoſe whom they thinke good; themſelues giuing audience in open Counſell vnto the greateſt perſons of the State, after that, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vpon them in their Chambers, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man muſt attend the definitions of their willes, vpon all ſorts of occurrences: Which to attaine, the difficulty to approch and ſpeake vnto them, puts many worthy and honeſt men that are about the King, cleane out of heart.</p>
            <p>And that which is moſt lamentable, while they in this manner effect their willes, to the great impoueriſhment of <hi>France,</hi> they buſie the King, by the meanes of idle and vaine-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, with Playes and Child-like exerciſes; things vnworthy the age of ſo great a King, whoſe actions ought to ſerue for an example to all his ſubiects.</p>
            <p>The aſſembly of the Nobles made in <hi>Roan,</hi> vnder a falſe pretence, to giue contentment to <hi>France,</hi> touching the ſo neceſſarie demands propounded to the generall States, was made onely to breake the policie, to the ruine of all the affaires of the Realme: cleane contrary to the intents and means that had been propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the aſſembly of the ſayd State and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, to the end, that they alone might diſpoſe of the Offices that ſhould be voyde, not only<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12685:7"/>to draw vnto themſelues great ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but alſo by that meanes to get creatures of their owne making in all the Townes of this Realme, is a manifeſt proofe, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre their owne particular profite before that of the State, and the publique benefit: Since which time, ſuch a number of Impoſts raiſed by extraordinarie meanes, haue beene impoſed vpon the people, that they are wholely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Queene-mother beſeecheth his Maieſtie to take order, as alſo to ſtay the courſe of the tirannies and vexations of Officers, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and Archers of the gabelles, which they daily exerciſe vpon all his Subiects, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly vpon thoſe of the Cleargie, and of the Nobilitie; a thing that neuer was vſed in the time of the King deceaſed, nor in the regencie of the ſaid Queene, but only ſince the time that theſe men, participating with them therin, haue giuen liberty and impunitie to all ſorts of pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, confuſions, murthers and cruelties.</p>
            <p>The ſale of Clark-ſhips ſo improperly made againſt the deceaſed Kings proiect, whereby his Maieſtie hath beene robbed of more then ſixe millions of Franckes, to inrich the parties afore-ſayd, with the treaſure of the Crowne, with the Penſions and mony which they haue vpon all the parts, and Farmes of this Realme, make a great maſſe of Treaſure, which they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble,<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12685:8"/>to make themſelues redoubted of the State, and by the means of this power, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe that would oppoſe themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this tyrannie.</p>
            <p>By all theſe meanes afore-ſayde, they haue made themſelues Maiſters, with licenſe of the Duke <hi>de Mombaſon,</hi> of the Citadell of <hi>Amiens, La Faire, Couſſy, Chauny,</hi> and of the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Iſle of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; <hi>Veruveil</hi> in <hi>Perche,</hi> with the Lieutenancie of <hi>Normandie,</hi> the more eaſily to ioyne
<hi>Quillebeuf,</hi> thereby to holde <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Roan</hi> in ſubiection.</p>
            <p>And not content to haue the Caſtelles of <hi>Amboiſe</hi> and
<hi>Nantes,</hi> vpon the Riuer of <hi>Loire,</hi> haue ſince ſought to draw into their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the gouernement of <hi>Britaine,</hi> Lieutenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the King, <hi>Blavet, Coucarraw,</hi> with <hi>Fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> which <hi>Ioſan Modere</hi> holdes; to the end to ioyne them all together, and by their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie make themſelues ſo puiſſant, that when the King himſelfe would pull them downe, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their too great power, ſo daungerous to his eſtate, he ſhould not be able: And when he ſhould chance to die, (which God forbid) they might diuide the Realme with his ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>Euery man likewiſe knowes, what meanes they haue vſed, to haue that litle which reſteth, which is the authoritie of Monſieur <hi>de Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille</hi> in <hi>Picardie,</hi> hauing no obſtacle but that, to hinder them from hauing the reſt of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12685:8"/>in that Prouince.</p>
            <p>Their follie and ignorance, hath ſhewed it ſelfe in the higheſt, degree, by ſhaking the bodie of the reformed Religion, by the innouation of the affaires of <hi>Beam,</hi> and the failing in the obſeruations of Treaties of Peace made with them, by the precedent Kings, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the conſequences, and fore-ſeeing of the perill that ſuch breaches may procure to this Realme.</p>
            <p>Touching forraine buſineſſes, it is a moſt great ſhame, that all the Ambaſſadors of Kings and Princes throughout Chriſtendome, are to make their Propoſitions, &amp; to take their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions from men ſo impertinent, and of ſo baſe condition; &amp; that the knowledge thereof is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the principall officers of the Crowne, and the ſtate of the Land.</p>
            <p>From thence it proceedeth, that the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, and ſtrict amitie which hath ſo long time bin contracted betweene the Crowns of
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> hath beene ſo badly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, with ſo many differences, as if we had no need of ſo good and faithfull friends. They haue in like ſort, proceeded with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> cauſing the King to take <hi>Barnavelts</hi> part, in his Treaſons againſt his Countrey, which are not to bee approoued by any good Chriſtians, nor true <hi>French men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meanes by them wrought to withdraw<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12685:9"/>the Gouernour of <hi>Orange,</hi> from the obedience which he oweth to his Maiſter and Lord, haue no leſſe ſtirred the courage of that great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, whoſe vertues and affection which hee hath alwayes borne to
<hi>Fraunce,</hi> deſerues not to be dealt withall in ſuch manner, touching that which concerneth his patrimony, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to humane right.</p>
            <p>To conclude, euery man may iudge, what miſerie, deſolation, ruine and calamitie, men of ſo baſe condition, voyde of all experience, capacitie, and honeſtie, may produce and cauſe in the management of ſo great a Realme. And what ſhame it is to <hi>France</hi> to indure and ſuffer ſuch infamie.</p>
            <p>In which diſorders and abuſes the Queene-Mother hauing moſt great &amp; notable intereſts, to haue ſpeedy remedy therein, not onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the extreame affection that ſhe beareth to the King, as his Mother, and the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his eſtate, but alſo becauſe of the great inconueniences that thereby may grow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; She moſt humbly beſeecheth his Maieſtie, to driue from his preſence, ſuch vnworthie and vncapable perſons, againſt whoſe inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, rapine, and treaſons, all <hi>France</hi> ought to crie vengeance; and to re-eſtabliſh all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Dukes, Peeres, and Officers of the Crowne, Lords and Gentlemen, in the free liberties of their functions, offices and dignities. And to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12685:9"/>entertaine and retaine about his Perſon, and in his Counſell, men that are vertuous, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to ſerue the State well and ſufficiently; that ſhee may be in ſuretie, neare to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie and her other Children, that ſhee may not haue cauſe of diſlike, that men that haue beene the cauſes of her ſo vnworthy entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould ſo vniuſtly be maintayned and vpholden, againſt ſo many good affections which they beare vnto him, and to his Realme. Which ſhee expecteth and hopeth for at his good inclination, being perſwaded that hee will not compare the amity of ſo dangerous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to hers, that hath had the honor to bring him into the world.</p>
            <p>If not, ſhe proteſteth to imploy all thoſe to whom ſhe hath the honour to appertaine, with her life, and thoſe that honour the memorie of the King deceaſed, againſt the perſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to haue reaſon and iuſtice; with proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſhee maketh before God, and men, not to haue any pretence againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, whom ſhee holdeth to be innocent of all the ſenſible diſpleaſures which haue beene done vnto her, but onely againſt thoſe that are the cauſe of all the miſchiefes which ſhee is forced to endure: In this proceeding hauing no other end nor intent, but only the encreaſe and aduancement of the greatnes and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of his Maieſtie, and his Realme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
